<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: scrum | Sohan's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://smsohan.com/blog/categories/scrum/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://smsohan.com/"/>
  <updated>2020-11-04T11:18:09-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://smsohan.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[SM Sohan]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The CGI story on agile scaling success on a large project]]></title>
    <link href="http://smsohan.com/blog/2009/09/09/cgi-story-on-agile-scaling-success-on/"/>
    <updated>2009-09-09T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://smsohan.com/blog/2009/09/09/cgi-story-on-agile-scaling-success-on</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class='post'>
<span class="Apple-style-span" style="border-collapse: collapse; font-family: arial; font-size: 13px; ">This intro is from the presenters:-<br /><blockquote>PAS was a joint venture development initiative by 4 major oil and gas<br />companies and CGI. Devon, Encana, Husky and Talisman joined with CGI to<br />develop a new Production and Revenue Application. Each company put 3 senior<br />business resources on the project. The development component of the PAS<br />initiative cost $35M over 5 years with up to 90 people on the team. This<br />presentation is on how we used Agile to achieve this mammoth undertaking.<br /><br />The product is currently running in production at 5 major oil and gas<br />companies with great reviews. It is also in production for several mid and<br />smaller sized companies. CGI is currently marketing the product.</blockquote>This was my first ever meet with the <a href="http://www.calgaryagile.com/">Calgary agile methods user group, CAMUG</a> and it was a great experience. Off late, I have been looking for my graduate research topic on agile methods, especially around scaling agile beyond a single team and this was just a perfect session for me.</span><div><span class="Apple-style-span" style="border-collapse: collapse; font-family: arial; font-size: 13px;"><br /></span></div><div><span class="Apple-style-span" style="border-collapse: collapse; font-family: arial; font-size: 13px;">I noted down a few of their discussed topics that I would like to share with my readers:</span></div><div><ol><li><span class="Apple-style-span" style="border-collapse: collapse; font-family: arial; font-size: 13px; ">The project continued in dev mode for 5 years, a $35M project.</span><br /></li><li><span class="Apple-style-span" style="border-collapse: collapse; font-family: arial; font-size: 13px; ">It started with only 3 members and extended to a team of 90 following Scrum+XP.</span><br /></li><li><span class="Apple-style-span" style="border-collapse: collapse; font-family: arial; font-size: 13px;">The project had 5 sponsoring companies or clients.</span></li><li><span class="Apple-style-span" style="border-collapse: collapse; font-family: arial; font-size: 13px;">They had 6 teams working in the same sprint cycles.</span></li><li><span class="Apple-style-span" style="border-collapse: collapse; font-family: arial; font-size: 13px;">In each team, there were significant members from the business working full time with the team onsite and in the same open-space arrangement.</span></li><li><span class="Apple-style-span" style="border-collapse: collapse; font-family: arial; font-size: 13px;">They had some 3000+ unit tests and also 300+ acceptance test.</span></li><li><span class="Apple-style-span" style="border-collapse: collapse; font-family: arial; font-size: 13px;">They automated all repetitive tests.</span></li><li><span class="Apple-style-span" style="border-collapse: collapse; font-family: arial; font-size: 13px;">The had external experts visiting them from time to time. Eric Evans once visited them and helped them getting better grasp on Domain Driven Design.</span></li><li><span class="Apple-style-span" style="border-collapse: collapse; font-family: arial; font-size: 13px;">There had been a $800K and one month deviation from the projected cost and timeline.</span></li></ol><span class="Apple-style-span" style="border-collapse: collapse; font-family: arial; font-size: 13px; ">They also discussed some issues related to working in a multi-team, multi-client project. I remember the following ones:-</span></div><div><ol><li>They had to balance between features/bug fixes.</li><li>The deployment was taken care of by the respective sponsors, not the teams.</li><li>They had issues with sprint backlog management.</li></ol><div>They highlighted some aspects with great emphasis:-</div><div><ol><li>Open communication is the key to success.</li><li>Onsite and full time real user availability is very important for such a big project.</li><li>Automated tests, partial pair programming and continuous integration is a big plus.</li><li>Staying co-located was really helpful.</li></ol><div>What about scaling beyond?</div><div><ol><li><span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-weight: bold;">I asked them, if they felt it would still be a similar success if there had been 12 teams or even more with 200 people or so. They said, it would be challenging.</span> But in response, they also said, following waterfall would make life much harder with such a big team, if at all it could be a success at the first place! Yes, I also believe this.</li><li>One of the audiences asked if they outsourced a part of the project and the response was 'No'. CGI has a big team in India with a very high CMM ranking, but the project manager and asst. project manager said, it would be much difficult for differing time zones. Also, it would be difficult to transfer the knowledge as well as replicate the value of onsite client presence. The development manager also added that, the cultural difference between an agile and CMM setup would also been an issue if they had to go for the off-shore team.</li></ol><div>The session was much more eventful than what I could compile. So, if you are anywhere near Calgary and interested about meeting agile practitioners from the industry, lets meet at the next meet! </div></div></div><div><br /></div></div><div><span class="Apple-style-span" style="border-collapse: collapse; font-family: arial; font-size: 13px; "> </span><br /></div><div><span class="Apple-style-span" style="border-collapse: collapse; font-family: arial; font-size: 13px;"> </span></div></div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Rambling stories from my days @ Code71 : Startup days]]></title>
    <link href="http://smsohan.com/blog/2009/08/08/rambling-stories-from-my-days-code71/"/>
    <updated>2009-08-08T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://smsohan.com/blog/2009/08/08/rambling-stories-from-my-days-code71</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class='post'>
<p>Sighs!</p>  <p>Back then, on Friday, May 26, 2006, I was a final year undergrad student at <a href="http://www.buet.ac.bd/cse">CSE, BUET</a>. I was looking for a part-time software dev job opportunity and found a little one page advert for a student job at asha-technologies (lately renamed as <a href="http://code71.com/" target="_blank">Code71</a>). Visited their website and thought it might be worth giving a try!</p>  <p>As usual, I was interviewed over phone and enjoyed a long 2 hour interview on premise. I found it really inspiring and gained more interest towards the job after this session. I started waiting for a response… but was pretty certain about a positive one!</p>  <p>Good things happen in quick successions in our lives. Agree?</p>  <p>I agree. Because I just started a soul-journey with my soul-mate, Shahana, on the March of 2006. Then got the job offer on the 26th of May! Couldn’t be happier. A job for me during that time was just beyond its compensation, it was an inspiration, opportunity to see the real world and being part of something bigger than myself.</p>  <p><img height="214" src="http://photos-g.ak.fbcdn.net/photos-ak-snc1/v3755/201/25/559702037/n559702037_2367230_3471408.jpg" width="222" /></p>  <p><em>Photo taken at Chhera dip (The Torn Island), St. Martins, Bangladesh. The last photograph taken with my first digital camera bought from my first month’s Salary!</em></p>  <p>I started my job on the 1st of June, 2006 at Asha-technologies. Asha-tech was still to find an office and <a href="http://syedraihan.com/" target="_blank">Omar</a> asked to meet him at his home office! That’s how it all started. We met a few times a week at Omar’s home until we moved to our office at the green building of green square at green road, Dhaka on the first of July.</p>  <p>Asha-tech signed up a client before it was even formed! So, once we moved into the office, we were building our first asha-tech product, an online loan financing gateway. We were enthusiastic about agile scrum/xp practices from the first day at office. The result was found in just less than 3 months. We rolled out our first release of the product. It was really a happy start. A fantastic start for a start-up. The client started generating revenue in less than 3 months of project inception!</p>  <p>The office setup was a small but adequate enough for our team. We installed long backup UPS (2 hours * 5 computers), A/C, IPS and dedicated internet connection with Wi-Fi. The work environment was full of fun. We were going for an outing to a team event every month and even more often going to delicious buffet places. We played table football and bowling… every time had a record breaking score and a new winner. We went swimming and believe me, <a href="http://syedraihan.com/" target="_blank">Omar</a> is as good a swimmer as he is a master in software technology. He would go to swimming with a flipper and flip like professional swimmers. He can even swim without using his hands/legs at all, lying side-on and in all such actions… I learned swimming keeping heads down and the easy way of breathing from him! Thanks!</p>  <p>Technologically we were maturing as well. Started using XPlanner for managing our project, attended daily standup meetings and started doing TDD. I won’t claim we got everything right at the first try… but, we were trying consistently, improving bit by bit… to this day.</p>  <p>For the most part, I was enjoying my job and became used to the pressure of a job + undergraduate studies. I said, good things happen in close succession. Another proof here! My first term final result with this job was a 4.0/4.0. I never scored 4.0 in a term before this nor had a 20+ hour/week job alongside my studies. </p>  <p>I strongly believe, my job taught me the attitude towards work, “plan, act and retrospect”. After over three years, I would suggest any new entrant in the software industry to start a career with passion. Its fun with passion. Its a win everyday with passion.</p></div>


<h2>Comments</h2>


<div class='comments'>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Fuad Omar</div>
<div class='content'>
Yes!Lot&#39;s of learning and fun and... of course, memory! Wish you all the best onward :-)</div>
</div>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Lesson#2: Pace Your Sprint Rightly]]></title>
    <link href="http://smsohan.com/blog/2009/06/15/lesson2-pace-your-sprint-rightly/"/>
    <updated>2009-06-15T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://smsohan.com/blog/2009/06/15/lesson2-pace-your-sprint-rightly</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class='post'>
<p>In my <a href="http://smsohan.blogspot.com/2009/06/lesson1-going-incremental-is-natural.html" target="_blank">previous post</a>, I said about being incremental. Here come the next thing, being “ITERATIVE”. A prefer the term Sprint than Iteration.</p>  <p>So, once you decided to take small increments, make sure you reach the targets sprinting.</p>  <p><a href="http://lh3.ggpht.com/_Gr1ozXzBWpM/SjX_DmKLDgI/AAAAAAAAAFo/xYRbI8rsbVI/s1600-h/sprint%5B3%5D.jpg"><img title="sprint" style="border-right: 0px; border-top: 0px; display: inline; border-left: 0px; border-bottom: 0px" height="260" alt="sprint" src="http://lh3.ggpht.com/_Gr1ozXzBWpM/SjX_EyH2GEI/AAAAAAAAAFs/c7e42WMAbEI/sprint_thumb%5B1%5D.jpg?imgmax=800" width="347" border="0" /></a> </p>  <p>I suggest you prepare for sprinting with the right techniques and tools. A few recommendations-</p>  <ol>   <li>Never miss a daily standup meeting. Spend only 2 minutes (or less) per person answering the three questions – what did you do yesterday, what’s on the plate for today and what is blocking the race?</li>    <li>Install visual clues for bringing the under the hood stuffs to daylight. Remember, being able to address the loopholes is the key. The solution usually follows automatically.</li> </ol>  <p>The key concept to internalize is, sprinting is a balance race. You need a good start and keep the momentum to reach the touch line on time. Its a small race and if you fall back, the touch line may seem too far to celebrate.</p>  <p>At Code71, <a href="http://scrumpad.com" target="_blank">ScrumPad</a>, is helping us in sprinting. Our sprints are two week sprints in most projects. We found the team communication holds a key in meeting the deadline. Since, within a sprint, someone of the team may need an unplanned vacation or an issue may arise out of the blue, the team needs to step up and put extra efforts. Again, visual clues help the team in keeping everybody posted timely.</p>  <p>If a team finds it difficult to meet the deadline and find the sprint length to be too small, then what? Should they linger the sprint length? NO. The solution is to even shorten the length. To make sure, the team can plan for short spans with better accuracy. Lingering the sprint length addresses the wrong disease and hence may not solve the problem.</p>  </div>


<h2>Comments</h2>


<div class='comments'>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Ashrafuzzaman</div>
<div class='content'>
I think 2 week sprint is a good sprint length and appropriate for most of the project.</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Ashrafuzzaman</div>
<div class='content'>
I think, two week sprint is a good sprint length and is appropriate for most of the projects.</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Tanvir Anowar</div>
<div class='content'>
I think for big projects and a big teams sprint lengths also should have to be big enough for a maximum outcome.</div>
</div>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Lesson#1: Going Incremental is Natural!]]></title>
    <link href="http://smsohan.com/blog/2009/06/03/lesson1-going-incremental-is-natural/"/>
    <updated>2009-06-03T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://smsohan.com/blog/2009/06/03/lesson1-going-incremental-is-natural</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class='post'>
<p>As Scrum and Agile processes tell you, do it in small sprints, 2 weeks preferably, and go incremental. Take a small piece at a time and sprint. </p>  <p><a href="http://lh3.ggpht.com/_Gr1ozXzBWpM/SidMvX7yttI/AAAAAAAAAFc/HvBvxUoFJdY/s1600-h/human-evolution-t10176%5B3%5D.jpg"><img title="human-evolution-t10176" style="border-right: 0px; border-top: 0px; display: inline; border-left: 0px; border-bottom: 0px" height="293" alt="human-evolution-t10176" src="http://lh4.ggpht.com/_Gr1ozXzBWpM/SidMx5T5PoI/AAAAAAAAAFg/0U5KZOhlt7c/human-evolution-t10176_thumb%5B1%5D.jpg?imgmax=800" width="407" border="0" /></a> </p>  <blockquote>   <p><em>I took this image from internet and credits to </em><a href="http://blogs.houstonpress.com/" target="_blank"><em>this site.</em></a></p> </blockquote>  <p>It’s easy to work out the Natural way than to defy it! If you are iterative and incremental, you are reaching towards the right hand side of the image! And to make the evolution faster, I suggest you try out Scrumming with <a href="http://scrumpad.com/" target="_blank">ScrumPad</a>. If you value “teaming” and “delivering” in sprints, <a href="http://scrumpad.com/" target="_blank">ScrumPad</a> will give you the oxygen to breathe while you sprint!</p>  <p>I suggest you follow a routine to iterate. At <a href="http://code71.com/" target="_blank">Code71</a>, we follow the below-</p>  <p><strong>Day 1:</strong> Plan for the next 9 days. Breakdown work items into smaller tasks, estimate at hours for each of the tasks and assign each task to an individual.</p>  <p><strong>Day 8: </strong>Release in test server (shadow version of the real production environment) and collect customer feedback.</p>  <p><strong>Day 9: </strong>Work on customer feedback and go live in production server. Always tag the version that is put in the production following the standard -</p>  <blockquote>   <p>R&lt;ProductReleaseVersion&gt;.S&lt;SprintNumber&gt;.B&lt;BuildNumber&gt;.P&lt;PatchNumber&gt;</p> </blockquote>  <p>This gives us the rollback point when there is any issue in the latest production deploy. Of course, we make sure we do not need to touch on the tags too often!</p>  <p>How are you sprinting? Let me know if you have a suggestion.</p></div>


<h2>Comments</h2>


<div class='comments'>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>titu</div>
<div class='content'>
Very helpful post for the beginner who want to learn about Scrum. In Code71 we are using ScrumPad from it&#39;s 2nd sprint. It helps us to speed up our project work as well as follow the Scrum. Also collaboration part is very helpful to communicate with clients specially for the team who work remotely.</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Tanvir</div>
<div class='content'>
Good post.I think incremental development process plays a pivotal role over waterfall in software industry(for most of our regular projects) nowadays.</div>
</div>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Its easier to get lost! Would you?]]></title>
    <link href="http://smsohan.com/blog/2009/06/03/its-easier-to-get-lost-would-you/"/>
    <updated>2009-06-03T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://smsohan.com/blog/2009/06/03/its-easier-to-get-lost-would-you</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class='post'>
<p>I was talking to a friend of mine, who started a IT start up and working full time with a few others to foster the business. He was telling me-</p>  <blockquote>   <p style="background-color: #fff200"><em>“We have 13 projects running at this moment. We are working our heart out. But, we are not finding any time to do Test Driven Development, Continuous Integration and all the good things…”</em></p> </blockquote>  <p>Well, I understand how it feels! As the title says, “Its easier to get lost!”</p>  <p><a href="http://lh4.ggpht.com/_Gr1ozXzBWpM/SiZB7nxv4hI/AAAAAAAAAFU/5Ye5BRK3vsE/s1600-h/maze%5B3%5D.jpg"><img title="maze" style="border-top-width: 0px; display: inline; border-left-width: 0px; border-bottom-width: 0px; border-right-width: 0px" height="338" alt="maze" src="http://lh5.ggpht.com/_Gr1ozXzBWpM/SiZB9jKM9iI/AAAAAAAAAFY/IUmlB7qh55o/maze_thumb%5B1%5D.jpg?imgmax=800" width="338" border="0" /></a>&#160;</p>  <p><em>Do you fancy getting stuck at this maze?</em></p>  <p>For startups, it is difficult to control the pulse. Because, you want to reach your billion dollar spot as early as possible, this week, or even earlier, today or even just in a few hours! And, as days go by, you start to feel the need for some process, to safeguard your efforts and quality, to hit the deadlines, to get in the rhythm of a sustainable pace.</p>  <p>But it may be really difficult to catch the ball at the first jump. We, at <a href="http://Code71.com" target="_blank">Code71</a>, believe we need to be visibly competent and confident about the quality of our work. And worked hard to get the gears together in motion. Now it is cliques great. We have got the people motivated to follow the best practices, the tools to “do more with less” and the process to ensure a “sustainable pace”. I advise, you do at least the following to learn to escape the maze from tomorrow-</p>  <ul>   <ul>     <li><strong>DIE</strong> for planning. Plan for short spans. We plan for two week sprints. </li>      <li>While planning, estimate honestly. Estimate all the hours necessary for following best practices. (producing automated test scripts may take 40% longer time, but bear with it) </li>      <li>Plan on your inputs. You cannot push your inputs. So, you may need to squeeze the output to match against your capacity. </li>      <li><strong>DIE</strong> to meet the deadline according to the plan. </li>   </ul> </ul>  <p>This is the mindset. You need to start believing to sustain. You need to plan honestly and never miss a deadline. After reaching the deadline, you retrospect. Find the loopholes and start filling those one by one. If you don’t see a loophole, find a ladder to reach higher. But do not place a ladder on a land mine!</p>  <p>Its not difficult if you have the preparation. To prepare, at a minimum do the following-</p>  <ul>   <li>Have a Continuous Integration (CI) server up and running 24x7 or <strong>DIE</strong>. (We use <a href="http://cruisecontrol.sourceforge.net/" target="_blank">CruiseControl</a>, its free and great) </li>    <li>Make your CI server to send build, test and coverage report for you. Keep an eye on the coverage report and <strong>DIE</strong> to remain well above the the 80% line. </li>    <li>Keep track of your activities for retrospect. We use <a href="http://scrumpad.com" target="_blank">ScrumPad</a>. It helps you to iterate, collaborate and deliver. </li> </ul>  <p>The keyword is <strong>“sustainable pace”</strong>. I found Scrum to address this sustainable pace really smartly. If you haven’t tried yet and looking for the loopholes to fill or the ladder to climb up, I suggest you learn about agile and <a href="http://www.goodagile.com/scrumprimer/index.html" target="_blank">Scrum</a>, find an expert and give it a try. It’s worth than you might have expected.</p>  <p>If you know a better way to keep delivering better, I will appreciate for sharing your idea to me. </p>  </div>


<h2>Comments</h2>


<div class='comments'>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>Sohan</div>
<div class='content'>
hmm... let me know if I can be of any help :-)</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>R O M E L</div>
<div class='content'>
my 1st comment was just a casual comment(please take it frienly comment)... please don&#39;t take it seriously... we tried to study about scrum and follow the principles many times but could not persist...</div>
</div>
<div class='comment'>
<div class='author'>R O M E L</div>
<div class='content'>
we thought of scrum so many times and couldn&#39;t organize ourselves... :(</div>
</div>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
