<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Onboarding | Sohan's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://smsohan.com/blog/categories/onboarding/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://smsohan.com/"/>
  <updated>2021-12-19T12:48:03-08:00</updated>
  <id>http://smsohan.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[SM Sohan]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Onboarding as a New Engineering Manager]]></title>
    <link href="http://smsohan.com/blog/2021/08/09/onboarding-as-a-new-engineering-manager/"/>
    <updated>2021-08-09T21:26:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://smsohan.com/blog/2021/08/09/onboarding-as-a-new-engineering-manager</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>"I promise to take care of you"</strong> - believe it or not, I spent hours to come up with this message to make a first impression as a newly hired manager at Microsoft. Everyone in my team had more context than me. I was a complete newbie, yet their manager. While I had been a manager for several years, I had never started a new job as a manager. I felt super vulnerable. In my previous job, I made an impression as a technical leader before transitioning into an engineering manager. But as a new hire and a manager at Microsoft, it was a brand new experience for me. I was worried. I really wanted to start on a positive note from the get go. I had three weeks in-between jobs and I went back to my favorite leadership books, podcasts and talks for ideas. I took many long walks thinking about a heartfelt message to provide psychological safety to my new team. After many iterations, I eventually came up with that sentence, carefully choosing each word.</p>

<p>Based on the feedback I received, I can tell my obsession on making a great first impression has been very effective. I focused on building trust as my number one priority. I proactively reached out and connected to my team members, my peers, and leaders above me. Following <a href="https://www.radicalcandor.com">radical candor</a> suggestions, I shared a bit of my life story to start the conversation. Then, I actively listened to them, asked for suggestions, and made sure I took notes and always followed up if there was an action item for me.</p>

<p>In this post, I am sharing an actual artifact from my first call with my peer and a fellow engineering manager <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/peterhess/">Peter Hess</a>. Peter has over 3 decades of industry experience, and he has been at Microsoft for over 15 years, worked in many key Microsoft products in several countries. During my first one:one with Peter, I shared my screen and asked him to talk about what he does as an engineering manager at Microsoft. It helped me to get a great visual of his job, but more importantly, it helped me understand the expectations of my job as a new hire. Click on "See the board" button below to see the output of this hour-long conversation between me and Peter. Even if you are not at Microsoft, I think this mind map shows a pretty well-rounded view of the engineering manager's job.</p>

<iframe width="100%" height="561" src="https://miro.com/app/embed/o9J_l3Yog3E=/?pres=1&frameId=3074457362331359883" frameBorder="0" scrolling="no" allowFullScreen></iframe>


<p>Of course, to succeed in a new job as a manager, you need to do more than just creating a first impression. The meta point is, prepare and take leadership in your own onboarding journey. It's worth it.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
