<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Leadership | Sohan's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://smsohan.com/blog/categories/leadership/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://smsohan.com/"/>
  <updated>2020-12-07T12:16:53-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://smsohan.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[SM Sohan]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[My YouTube Playlist for Leadership]]></title>
    <link href="http://smsohan.com/blog/2020/11/04/youtube/"/>
    <updated>2020-11-04T10:29:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://smsohan.com/blog/2020/11/04/youtube</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This summer I was interviewing for a new job. This was the first time I was interviewing for an engineering manager role. Soon I realized  these interviews were wildly different from interviews for developer roles. During typical developer interviews, I solved coding and system design problems and discussed personal aspirations in behavioral interviews. In contrast, leadership interview qeustions were really open-ended. Honestly, I found it very hard to answer these questions concisely. Often I could form a crisp answer to these questions only after the interview had finished :-( Here are some example questions:</p>

<ol>
<li>What is your management philosophy?</li>
<li>Tell me when you had to deal with uncertainty.</li>
<li>Tell me about when you had to motivate a team even though you personally disagreed with the project.</li>
<li>Tell me when you innovated as a manager.</li>
</ol>


<p>I did poorly in my first few interviews because how unprepared I was to answer these questions. I got truly frustrated. So, I started looking at YouTube to see how today's inspiring leaders answer these questions. Here's a list of YouTube channels that I found to be very resourceful.</p>

<ol>
<li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/c/DavidRubenstein/videos?view=0&amp;sort=p&amp;shelf_id=8">David Rubnstein Show</a>: 25 minute very high quality interviews with present and former leaders in business and technology.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLxq_lXOUlvQAwaY_9K4ZFH9Xdar9WzCaL">View From the Top - Stanford</a>: Hour long interview sessions with renowned leaders.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLnsTB8Q5VgnVzh1S-VMCXiuwJglk5AV--">Technology Enabled Blitzscaling</a>: Hour long interview sessions focusing on technology and startup leadership.</li>
</ol>


<p>Watching these videos I developed some strategies for concisely answering leadership related questions with authenticity. I'd so love to do a formal research and write up on this topic some time. But for now, here's the raw data for your enjoyment.</p>

<p>Go ahead and watch!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How am I Developing the People I Support as a People Leader?]]></title>
    <link href="http://smsohan.com/blog/2019/03/26/how-am-i-developing-the-people-i-support-as-a-people-leader/"/>
    <updated>2019-03-26T08:29:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://smsohan.com/blog/2019/03/26/how-am-i-developing-the-people-i-support-as-a-people-leader</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>After being a people leader at work for the past six years, I’m now going through a phase of introspection. Essentially, I’m trying to understand my own philosophy about people leadership so that I can clearly communicate it to the people that I support.</p>

<p>My most important realization is, <strong>people leadership is all about developing people</strong>. What I mean by this is, for everyone I’m supporting, I must carefully build a plan that provides them with the opportunities to stay motivated so that they can thrive. With this goal, once I wrote down my understanding of what motivates each of the people I support, it was quite eye opening to see the differences among people. Going through this process, I also realized how unprepared I was in terms of providing them with a clear career path to achieve their best.</p>

<p>If you’re interested, I’ve shared a template of the <strong>people development document</strong> here.</p>

<p><code>
Name: ___
Date:___
Current role: ___
Motivation: ___
Upcoming opportunity in the next three months:___
Upcoming opportunity in the next year:___
</code></p>

<p>I consider this to be a living document as people often develop new interests and the opportunities at work change with time. But keeping a clear log of each individual’s career is a great way to establish and manage expectations. You can build this with the the individuals directly and update it when you meet for one-on-one feedbacks. As a lead, when you collaboratively build this, you empower them and build a trusting relationship as you both see how the motivations align with the work.</p>

<p>From the past 13 years of my time in the industry, working for 5 different companies, personally I’ve always felt a little under-informed about how my leaders planned a career development for me. Through my introspection of being a people leader, I realized I didn’t honestly appreciate the need for such clarity among the people I supported. So, I wanted to change it. And found the written document to be a simple yet surprisingly powerful tool to fill this void.</p>

<p>Now, if you’re a people leader, I’d recommend doing this exercise with your people. You’ll be pleasantly surprised by the outcome.</p>

<p>If you aren’t a people leader, you can write it down for yourself and ask your leader to collaborate on it. This way, when you have a one-on-one, you both will have the same reference document to focus on.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
