<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Design | Sohan's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://smsohan.com/blog/categories/design/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://smsohan.com/"/>
  <updated>2021-02-19T09:46:29-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://smsohan.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[SM Sohan]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Micro Design Critic: Microsoft Word vs. Apple Pages]]></title>
    <link href="http://smsohan.com/blog/2019/05/29/microsoft-word-vs-apple-pages/"/>
    <updated>2019-05-29T10:44:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://smsohan.com/blog/2019/05/29/microsoft-word-vs-apple-pages</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/WordsVsPages.png" alt="MsWordVsApplePages" />
Showing a Screenshot of Microsoft Word for Mac and Apple Pages</p>

<p>This is what you get by default when you open a blank document on both editors.
I love that Apple Pages puts a deep focus on the content. If you haven't used it, I'd
recommend trying it out. I know Microsoft Word has a known face, so
you're likely used to all the distractions that sorrounds the content.
But, if you can, give Apple Pages a try.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Configure Me Not]]></title>
    <link href="http://smsohan.com/blog/2013/11/03/configure-me-not/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-03T21:29:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://smsohan.com/blog/2013/11/03/configure-me-not</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Configuration in software provides a method to build systems that can
adapt to different configurations. For example, if a website's language and
date/currency formats are configurable, then it can be configured to
support multiple languages and regional formats. Configuration makes it
possible to deliver such features without needing a log of change in the
application source code.</p>

<p>However, this notion of flexibility that configuration provides can be a trap at times. I've a definition of configurable as follows:</p>

<blockquote><p>A configurable must have at least two configurations.</p></blockquote>

<p>This is another way of saying YAGNI. But I find this to be more specific
than YAGNI, as it quantifies and makes it apparent.</p>

<p>Here are a few examples to illustrate my definition.</p>

<ol>
<li><p> <strong>Custom interfaces with a single implementation.</strong></p>

<p> Interfaces are often times thought as a configurable component, as a new
 implementation can be used in place of an old one without changing the
 code that uses it.</p>

<p> Except, if your interface only ever have one implementation, this
 provides a false notion of flexibility. In practice, I've seen for most
 custom interfaces, a new implementation almost always needs a change in
 the original interface which doesn't really make it configurable
 anymore.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Default arguments in methods that are never passed a non-default
value.</strong></p>

<p> Default arguments are great, as they often times simplify the common
 case. However, if a method with a default argument is never called
 with a non-default value, it's simply not worth using a default argument. Use a local variable instead.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Configuration key value pairs where there's only one value.</strong></p>

<p> Since magic numbers and hardcoded strings are bad, it's tempting to use
 the configuration file to hold such values. However, if there's only one
 such value, it's probably a constant and not a configurable object.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Exhaustively validating method parameters against all possible but unused values.</strong></p>

<p> If you're writing a method that's only gonna be called from another
 method in your project, you probably know what you're passing to the
 method. Validating for different negative inputs to such methods provide
 a sense of robustness without really adding any value to it.</p></li>
</ol>


<p>Hoping, the definition makes sense. Would love to hear your
opinion and examples of configure me not.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
