<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Other | Sohan's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://smsohan.com/blog/categories/other/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://smsohan.com/"/>
  <updated>2020-10-12T10:26:02-06:00</updated>
  <id>http://smsohan.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[SM Sohan]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Context]]></title>
    <link href="http://smsohan.com/blog/2020/09/15/context/"/>
    <updated>2020-09-15T13:08:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://smsohan.com/blog/2020/09/15/context</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/misfit.jpg" alt="Misfit" /></p>

<p>Image credits to <a href="https://flic.kr/p/5kNo6M">NCinDC</a></p>

<p>Context is everything. Due to a context mismatch projects such as exporting democracy, agile transformations, building startups, losing weight, mindfulness or anything you can think of fail to repeat.</p>

<p>Context is formed by <strong>why / what / who / when / where / how</strong>, each of these being a critcial part. Most often it's common to focus on the how alone - forgetting the rest of the context while adopting a recipe for success in business. Some get overly <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Simon_Sinek">influenced by speakers</a> and focus on only a subset of the context. Reality is, it's almost impossible to find an excact duplicate of any one context. So, while copying solutions from one context, we must adapt to account for the uniqueness of our own context.</p>

<p>A lot of innovation lies in the context gap - where one can find clever ways to adapt solutions from one context into another. I'll give you one such example, did you know Uber runs a motorcycle based rideshare in <a href="https://www.uber.com/en-BD/blog/dhaka/dhaka-moto/">many countries</a>?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Play at Work]]></title>
    <link href="http://smsohan.com/blog/2019/07/04/play-at-work/"/>
    <updated>2019-07-04T16:03:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://smsohan.com/blog/2019/07/04/play-at-work</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/paper_plane.jpg" alt="paper plane" /></p>

<p><small>
Image source: <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hgz/">Kalvis</a>
</small></p>

<p>"I am a mango".</p>

<p>First, mangoes are in-season, and I still remember the
juicy sweetness of the mango I had just the night before. So, when the coach
asked each of us to be a fruit, I didn't think twice. One of my
coworkers was a kiwi, another one apple, and so on. The idea was to
group us
by color, then by size. This got us, twenty people in the class, moving and engaged. It was part
of a two-day design thinking course. The coaches used the fruit game to
bring some energy into the room as well as to pave the way for the next
exercise - grouping a bunch of ideas by cost and the level of
innovation.</p>

<p>I find that professional trainers bring play at work, especially for
sessions that span hours or days. However, on a typical day to day
business, I don't see much play activity at work. Hoping to bring in
some play activities to my work going forward. Here are some ideas for
play activities based on what I saw so far:</p>

<p>Paper planes: Having small groups build paper planes and the winner has
the most number of planes crossing a line.</p>

<p>Catch and throw: A ball or a ball-like object changing hands and the person
catching must find someone that didn't catch it already.</p>

<p>Portrait: Everyone draws a portrait of another person looking at their
face without looking at the paper.</p>

<p>Quiz: An online quiz that maintains a leaderboard throughout a session.</p>

<p>Exercise: Getting everyone out of their seats to do a quick one-minute
exercise.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Annual letter]]></title>
    <link href="http://smsohan.com/blog/2016/12/18/annual-letter-to-myself-and-to-the-www/"/>
    <updated>2016-12-18T23:35:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://smsohan.com/blog/2016/12/18/annual-letter-to-myself-and-to-the-www</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3>2016 Highs and lows</h3>

<h4>Baby #2, it's a girl</h4>

<p>Shera, our little daughter, was born this year. She has been happy, healthy, and an absolute source of joy. Almost hard to believe that we somehow sustained the pregnancy period of my wife, while also running after our active toddler son, Shopoth. Such a pleasure to see the two already reaching for one another, cuddling, giggling, and occasionally fighting.</p>

<h4>Canadian Citizenship, eh!</h4>

<p>I'm very glad and proud to be a Canadian citizen starting this year. I just realized that I spent 21% of my life in Canada already! For those of you that haven't been to Canada yet, you should visit some time for it's one of the most beautiful places on earth with people of good heart.</p>

<h4>Life &amp; Work, well balanced</h4>

<p>Mostly doing 40-hour work weeks and working from home once / week. The team I'm managing has built up on solid foundations now. This is super exciting to see motivated people working on challenging projects and consistently delivering quality outcome.</p>

<h4>Personal finances, thumbs-down</h4>

<p>While the return on my experimental investing portfolio has been great, I didn't make good on the car-buying decision. Ended up getting into a 4-year lease on a car that has more seats than our living room, and we only really needed it for the summer while we had family with us.</p>

<h4>Health, got lazy</h4>

<p>Honestly, it was a tough year to dedicate time for health. I know you're thinking "it's a lame excuse." On the bright side, our team won the friendly soccer tournament this summer, and played soccer almost each of the Friday nights starting October. However, I got lazy otherwise. Probably also just too tired from the kids and housework at times.</p>

<h4>Relationships, so-so</h4>

<p>Met some friends and had a few phone calls with friends throughout the year. But, I failed to connect with relatives outside my first family. This is likely a result of being so far physically, but also something that only gets worse unless actively taken care of.</p>

<h4>Remote work, didn't work too well</h4>

<p>We spent the first month of 2016 in Bangladesh with family. It was my first time experiment working remotely with a 12 hour timezone difference. It was fun to start. But I could feel the stress of having to stay up till 2-3AM each night and dealing with Internet latency issues. While I had a decent accommodation and a makeshift office arrangement, it got harder to get enough sleep. Next time if I work remotely, I will limit my commitment to midnight.</p>

<h4>Misc. things</h4>

<ol>
<li>Continued our charity program financing to support education in Bangladesh.</li>
<li>I didn't have any public speaking session in the whole year for the first time in past 10 years.</li>
<li>Ended up spending too much time on social media for little gain.</li>
<li>While made some progress towards my PhD thesis, didn't submit any paper.</li>
</ol>


<p>There's a 2nd post coming about the new year's resolution. Come back in a few days.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[RailsConf 2015]]></title>
    <link href="http://smsohan.com/blog/2015/05/08/railsconf-2015/"/>
    <updated>2015-05-08T14:11:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://smsohan.com/blog/2015/05/08/railsconf-2015</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I have finally been able to attend a RailsConf, the 2015 edition was my first ever. And I got to say hi to people like @dhh, @wycats, and many more. Thanks Cisco for sponsoring this trip.</p>

<p>The attendance on the conference was totally amazing, heaven knows how many, but it looked like a couple thousands of rails developers attended the @dhh keynote. And @dhh delivered a good one. Unlike the last year's talk, this year it didn't cause a huge noise because it was mostly about announcing new features of rails to be released with Rails 5. However, some rails core committers took it to twitter to share their surprise when they heard about Action Cable for the first time at the keynote. But everyone kept it limited to some trolling!</p>

<p>The @tenderlove keynote was the one that I really liked of all the talks that I attended. He is expected to be funny, and in front of a hall full of rails developers, he indeed delivered a fun talk, mixed with some serious performance improvement techniques and amazing new feature announcements coming with Rails 5. I envy his presentation skills. He talked about performance testing bundler on a system with a hundred thousand gems. It was quite fascinating to see how he was able to improve a polynomial time algorithm into a constant time one to cut down bundler boot up time, essentially speeding up all rails and ruby applications. Great work.</p>

<p>Of course, the conference talks are made available on videos and are open for anyone to watch. However, attending a conference is more about meeting people on the hallways than about listening to their talks. At least to me, that's what I want from a conference. For example, I met Chris, a guy that was working on a gem to wrap InfluxDB interface under an active record like abstraction. Thought that was cool. Met a guy named Charles, who works for a startup company writing software for automated airline landing. Met a guy named John, who writes his own online game.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Lessons Learned: Entrepreneurship and Innovation Course]]></title>
    <link href="http://smsohan.com/blog/2014/12/09/lessons-learned-entrepreneurship-and-innovation-course/"/>
    <updated>2014-12-09T14:32:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://smsohan.com/blog/2014/12/09/lessons-learned-entrepreneurship-and-innovation-course</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This fall semester, I signed for the Entrepreneurship and Innovation course (ENTI 781) at the Haskyne Business School of University of Calgary. Wanted to capture my thoughts on this course for my readers here.</p>

<p>First, the course was unconventional since there are very little academic material to teach entrepreneurship and innovation. The teacher, Olga Petricevic, did a decent job of collecting materials comprising of academic papers, case studies, newspaper articles and YouTube videos as well as bringing in a local entrepreneur for a lecture one day. But none of these were the highlights for me.</p>

<p>The course had a few assignments and I liked a couple to be specific. In one assignment, the students were asked to find a project in Indigogo or Kickstarter to put their own money. This was eyeopening, as I had hard time finding a project that looked to have any potential to become a successful venture. Moreover, even if I liked it, there were almost no incentive to "donate" your money since all you got was a token for your money in a way that you bear the risk without any potential for a profit.</p>

<p>The other assignment was about compiling a list of 50 things that bug me in everyday life. This was the most fun assignment of the semester and I had a decent list with bugs such as:</p>

<pre><code>1. Did I leave the stove on while leaving the house?
2. Vacuum cleaning the stairs.
3. Finding a plumber NOW.
4. Waiting at airport.
...
</code></pre>

<p>All in all, the worst assignment was the group assignment. The group I worked with was very collaborative and did a great job in keeping everyone in sync with clear messaging around individual expectations. However, the project itself sucked. We were asked to create a stupid business plan for a venture around "watervate" - innovative solution to save water that could turn into a profitable business. In an entrepreneurship course, the deliverable was a business plan, with detailed text on the product, marketing, strategy, financial data etc. that were completely fake. The fakeness of the whole assignment made it super boring for me.</p>

<p><strong>After finishing this course, I actually have a better trust in online education.</strong> The course was unplugged, so students had to keep digital devices off. But on one class the rules were lax because it was about presenting. I saw people browsing sports scores, watching memes, playing games and random youtube videos etc. right  in the class. These students are mostly MBA students, holding a good day job, but it hurt my eyes to see them paying so little respect to the fellow students presenting.</p>

<p>Online education on the other hand, is so much so for self driven students that, I expect them to carry much respect for their own time. I suggest people taking online courses to save their money and time and also to learn better than traditional classroom settings.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
