<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Career | Sohan's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://smsohan.com/blog/categories/career/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://smsohan.com/"/>
  <updated>2020-12-24T19:18:16-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://smsohan.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[SM Sohan]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA["You are Unfrogattable"]]></title>
    <link href="http://smsohan.com/blog/2020/12/24/you-are-unfrogettable/"/>
    <updated>2020-12-24T18:39:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://smsohan.com/blog/2020/12/24/you-are-unfrogettable</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/CiscoCard.jpg" alt="card" /></p>

<p><small>This card is a parting gift from beloved team. (Catherine, I know you made it)</small></p>

<p>This post is dedicated to my team at Cisco. I put a lot of my passion and care into building and being part of a great team during my time at Cisco, eight amazing years between 2012 to 2020. It was the privilege of a lifetime to be able to learn from and mentor an amazing group of people while building a product together.</p>

<p>Our memories work in a fascinating way. At Cisco, I put most of my working hours on actual work such as understanding and sharing project scope, designing and building solutions, responding to customer support requests, interviewing, presenting, etc. But just after four months, now that I think about my time at Cisco, none of the actual work takes the centre stage in my memory. Instead, the memory is filled with incredible life stories I heard during the short walks I took at the park for one:one meetings, or relaxed and often-long Friday lunches, or a giving someone a safe space when they felt vulnerable. It's a reminder that when it's all done and dusted - what remains is the people and relationships we build with them. I'm so glad to get this card in the mail after I left and I'll forever remember this gesture.</p>

<p>What better can a man wish for than being "unfrogettable"?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Where to Learn: 10 Ways I Do]]></title>
    <link href="http://smsohan.com/blog/2020/11/18/where-to-learn/"/>
    <updated>2020-11-18T10:51:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://smsohan.com/blog/2020/11/18/where-to-learn</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/learning.png" alt="learning" /></p>

<p>When talking to people, I'm always interested to know how they learn. This image above shows a view of how I personally learn. Here's some context about the items on the diagram:</p>

<ol>
<li>Online-courses: I love O'Reilly learning. Their video courses are split into 5 minute lectures. For example, I took their Kotlin course to learn the language.</li>
<li>Books: Books are great for curated content, but it takes dedicated time. Most of the time, I have one book that I read. Current interest is on leadership and business.</li>
<li>Hands-on: A lot of people learn by doing. I do the same, but mostly at a hello world level instead of going too deep into new things.</li>
<li>Podcasts: This is my most passive form of learning, mostly when I'm walking or driving.</li>
<li>People: I keep in touch with people and ask them about what they are learning.</li>
<li>Twitter: I admit, I spend too much time on Twitter. But occasionally, people share interesting things.</li>
<li>YouTube videos: I watch conference talks such as InfoQ, DotNet, Rails, Ruby, Goto, and AWS.</li>
<li>News: I follow Hacker News mostly for tech and business news. And then there's following stock market news about new business innovations.</li>
<li>Interviews: I watch inteview shows on YouTube as I'm a big fan of biographical content.</li>
<li>Open-source: I follow a bunch of open-source projects or just read code from time to time to learn about how the passionate and expert developers craft code.</li>
</ol>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Learn to Get and Give Feedback]]></title>
    <link href="http://smsohan.com/blog/2020/11/12/learn-to-get-and-give-feedback/"/>
    <updated>2020-11-12T11:45:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://smsohan.com/blog/2020/11/12/learn-to-get-and-give-feedback</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/feedback.jpg" alt="Feedback" /></p>

<p><small>Photo credits to <a href="https://flic.kr/p/2edx7Za">GotCredit</a></small></p>

<p>Here’s a personal story about getting a feedback. For context, English is my second language. I grew up speaking Bangla as my primary language. I learned reading and writing English in school - grammar first. I had only started speaking English much later in my life, in my mid-twenties. So, I often struggle with the informal form of the language. With this context, here’s an excerpt of a one:one chat conversation at work (from memory):</p>

<p><strong>Catherine</strong>: Sohan, I have a question when you have time.<br/>
<strong>Me</strong>: Shoot me.<br/>
<strong>Catherine</strong>: Haha. It’s not “shoot me”. I think you mean just “shoot”. When you say “shoot me” it means…</p>

<p>In this case, Catherine genuinely cared and had the courage to share this feedback about my improper use of English. I love getting such direct and timely feedback.</p>

<p>Here, I’m sharing links to some content that I found to be high quality resources to learn about  feedback. Hope you’ll enjoy.</p>

<ol>
<li>Radical Candor Talk - <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=4yODalLQ2lM">The Surprising Secret to Being a Good Boss</a></li>
<li>Podcast: <a href="https://podcasts.apple.com/ca/podcast/ep-7-how-to-get-feedback-from-your-boss/id1188489488?i=1000381196889">How to Get Feedback From Your Boss</a></li>
<li>Podcast: <a href="https://podcasts.apple.com/ca/podcast/ep-16-take-feedback-like-a-boss/id1188489488?i=1000384606048">Take Feedback Like A Boss</a></li>
<li>Podcast: <a href="https://podcasts.apple.com/ca/podcast/ep-8-how-to-give-feedback-to-your-boss/id1188489488?i=1000381487680">How to Give Feedback To Your Boss</a></li>
<li>Book chapter: <a href="https://www.norulesrules.com">Max up Candor: A Circle of Feedback</a></li>
</ol>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Working With Me]]></title>
    <link href="http://smsohan.com/blog/2020/02/08/working-with-me/"/>
    <updated>2020-02-08T12:38:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://smsohan.com/blog/2020/02/08/working-with-me</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Since I commonly work with a diverse group of people, this post is a way for me to broadcast some quick tricks that may help our working relationship. When we work together, let's do this:</p>

<p><strong>Trust</strong> is only earned when it's mutual. Let's work with this shared belief.</p>

<p><strong>Context</strong> is everything. Most importantly, show me <strong>why</strong> we need to work on something. If the answer isn't clear in your mind, we can work together to build a crisp context.</p>

<p><strong>Solutions</strong> for problems you're raising. Ideally, you've already thought about a few solutions with some measure of feasibility for each, and you come with an open mind. I know you care about the problem only if you spent some time thinking about a few solutions.</p>

<p><strong>Clarity</strong> between your evidence and assumptions. Assumptions are often essential to move ahead, but treating assumptions as evidence can be harmful.</p>

<p><strong>Output</strong> is the focus, our egos aren't. That said, let's be mutually respectful.</p>

<p><strong>Time</strong> is managed. Let's manage our expectations given the time we have. Blaming the shortage of time shows a lack of skill.</p>

<p><strong>Writing</strong> is a great thought exercise and good write-up scales infinitely. Let's write and rewrite our thoughts, specially when we're unclear about those.</p>

<p><strong>Standup comedies, biography, soccer, politics, investment, tech, leadership, Netflix, movies, and similar topics</strong> are cool. Sorry, not much of a Hockey or Basket Ball fan. Mostly a passive music listener and happy to listen whatever is on radio or a YouTube playlist.</p>

<p>If you have a similar list, I'd be happy to read and respect it. Please send along.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Internal Trainings]]></title>
    <link href="http://smsohan.com/blog/2019/06/27/internal-trainings/"/>
    <updated>2019-06-27T13:31:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://smsohan.com/blog/2019/06/27/internal-trainings</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/design_thinking.jpg" alt="design_thinking" /></p>

<p><small>
Design Thinking course, Cisco Calgary Office, AB, 2019
</small></p>

<p>One benefit of working at Cisco is access to the many learning and development resources. Our learning and development org arranges hundreds of courses throughout the year. Moreover, we have a reimbursement program for external courses, conferences, books, and subscriptions to online learning programs and publications.</p>

<p>In the past 6 years, I have immensely benefitted from these resources. Here's a list of the learning resources I've used.</p>

<ol>
<li><a href="https://learning.oreilly.com">Safari books online</a>, aka O'Reilly learning: In the past 3 years, have taken 3 online trainings and 7 books on this platform so far.</li>
<li>Design thinking, 2019: A two-day course taught by consultants about how to apply the principles of design thinking to communicate and derive solutions to complex problems.</li>
<li>Mindfulness, 2019: A 5-week program taught by consultants, with one hour per week, where I learned about staying mindful and effective at work amid all the chaos that surrounds it.</li>
<li><a href="http://tufte.com">Tufte one-day course</a>, 2019: Attended a course taught by Edward Tufte on data visualization and learned about the principles that make compelling data visualization.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.sans.org/course/hacker-techniques-exploits-incident-handling">SANS incident response</a>, 2018: A packed week-long program where I learned to think like a hacker by learning about and then hacking some interesting vulnerabilities in systems.</li>
<li><a href="https://dcloud-cms.cisco.com/demo_news/cisco-r00tcamp-lab-v1">Cisco R00tcamp</a>, 2017: A packed week-long program where I learned hands-on pen-testing techniques to build more secure software.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.cisco.com/c/en/us/products/security/threat-hunting-workshop.html">Cisco threat-hunting</a>, 2017: A daylong course to find root case that triggered a security threat using integrated Cisco tools, including the product I build with our team.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.railsconf.com/2015/">RailsConf</a>, 2015: It was a big opportunity to meet the community and bring some of their practices in-house. For example, we started using <a href="https://www.bugsnag.com">BugSnag</a> after learning about it in the conference.</li>
</ol>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
