<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Career | Sohan's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://smsohan.com/blog/categories/career/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://smsohan.com/"/>
  <updated>2021-12-11T19:39:33-08:00</updated>
  <id>http://smsohan.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[SM Sohan]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Onboarding as a New Engineering Manager]]></title>
    <link href="http://smsohan.com/blog/2021/08/09/onboarding-as-a-new-engineering-manager/"/>
    <updated>2021-08-09T21:26:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://smsohan.com/blog/2021/08/09/onboarding-as-a-new-engineering-manager</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>"I promise to take care of you"</strong> - believe it or not, I spent hours to come up with this message to make a first impression as a newly hired manager at Microsoft. Everyone in my team had more context than me. I was a complete newbie, yet their manager. While I had been a manager for several years, I had never started a new job as a manager. I felt super vulnerable. In my previous job, I made an impression as a technical leader before transitioning into an engineering manager. But as a new hire and a manager at Microsoft, it was a brand new experience for me. I was worried. I really wanted to start on a positive note from the get go. I had three weeks in-between jobs and I went back to my favorite leadership books, podcasts and talks for ideas. I took many long walks thinking about a heartfelt message to provide psychological safety to my new team. After many iterations, I eventually came up with that sentence, carefully choosing each word.</p>

<p>Based on the feedback I received, I can tell my obsession on making a great first impression has been very effective. I focused on building trust as my number one priority. I proactively reached out and connected to my team members, my peers, and leaders above me. Following <a href="https://www.radicalcandor.com">radical candor</a> suggestions, I shared a bit of my life story to start the conversation. Then, I actively listened to them, asked for suggestions, and made sure I took notes and always followed up if there was an action item for me.</p>

<p>In this post, I am sharing an actual artifact from my first call with my peer and a fellow engineering manager <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/peterhess/">Peter Hess</a>. Peter has over 3 decades of industry experience, and he has been at Microsoft for over 15 years, worked in many key Microsoft products in several countries. During my first one:one with Peter, I shared my screen and asked him to talk about what he does as an engineering manager at Microsoft. It helped me to get a great visual of his job, but more importantly, it helped me understand the expectations of my job as a new hire. Click on "See the board" button below to see the output of this hour-long conversation between me and Peter. Even if you are not at Microsoft, I think this mind map shows a pretty well-rounded view of the engineering manager's job.</p>

<iframe width="100%" height="561" src="https://miro.com/app/embed/o9J_l3Yog3E=/?pres=1&frameId=3074457362331359883" frameBorder="0" scrolling="no" allowFullScreen></iframe>


<p>Of course, to succeed in a new job as a manager, you need to do more than just creating a first impression. The meta point is, prepare and take leadership in your own onboarding journey. It's worth it.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Can I Have a Career as a Frontend Engineer?]]></title>
    <link href="http://smsohan.com/blog/2021/02/19/frontend-engineering/"/>
    <updated>2021-02-19T08:27:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://smsohan.com/blog/2021/02/19/frontend-engineering</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In my current role at Microsoft, I'm working on a UI SDK product. I
hear this concern from some of my team members. More specifically,
here's a paraphrased version of what I hear:</p>

<blockquote><p>"I talked to my friends in software and they told me it's better to work
on the backend or full-stack to have a fast-tracked career."</p></blockquote>

<p>First, I do agree that there are generally more full-stack or backend
engineering jobs than purely frontend jobs. I also agree that there's a
general perception that frontend is easy / bunch of scripts / not real
engineering, yada yada...</p>

<p>However, I think it's a short-sighted view. Let me make my point here.</p>

<p><strong>Let's imagine the UI and UX of a familiar product, Google Maps.</strong> You can
use Google Maps on your browser or natively on the phone. You can embed
Google Maps within your own app on these platforms as well. You can ask
Google Maps to give you navigation direction for walking, biking,
driving, or ask it to show realtime transit and traffic infomation. If you
take a detour, it'll show you new directions on the fly. You can see the
map view, or the 3D view, or a camera view of a location. At night, you
can see the dark-mode. It'll show you how many lanes you have on a road,
and how fast you can legally go, in realtime. It'll let you share your location in
realtime with your buddy. You can search using your voice and it'll also
give you turn by turn voice guidance. Let's not mention avoiding
toll-free roads, u-turns, etc.</p>

<p><strong>I hope you see the engineering challenge I see in the above
paragraph.</strong>
Very few engineers I know can architect a system such as Google Maps.
Since a lot of the engineers choose the path of backend engineering,
it's incredibly hard to find frontend engineers who can pull high impact
projects. If you consider yourself above
average, and you probably are if you're reading this blog, you should
not follow the path of the average. Instead, if you like building visual
products and obsessing about delighting millions or billions of users,
you can have a very rewarding and fast-paced career in frontend
engineering.</p>

<p><strong>Most of your engineering knowledge is transferrable,</strong> irrespective of
what part of the stack you work on. After all, you'll learn to work with
people, delight customers, build systems that are robust, scalable,
secure, compliant, testable... So, you can move into a different part of
the stack at will as long as your foundation is strong.</p>

<p>Modern frontend engineering is complex, but it's powered by innovative
tools. Most of the tooling is open-source and the community is
vibrant with lots of conferences and meetups around the world. As a
frontend engineer, you can create an outsized impact and differentiate
yourself from the masses.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA["you're unfrogettable"]]></title>
    <link href="http://smsohan.com/blog/2020/12/24/you-are-unfrogettable/"/>
    <updated>2020-12-24T18:39:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://smsohan.com/blog/2020/12/24/you-are-unfrogettable</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/CiscoCard.jpg" alt="card" /></p>

<p><small>This card is a parting gift from my beloved team. (Catherine, I know you made it)</small></p>

<p>This post is dedicated to my team at Cisco. I put a lot of my passion and care into building and being part of a great team during my time at Cisco, eight amazing years between 2012 to 2020. It was the privilege of a lifetime to be able to learn from and mentor an amazing group of people while building a product together.</p>

<p>Our memories work in a fascinating way. At Cisco, I put most of my working hours on actual work such as understanding and sharing project scope, designing and building solutions, responding to customer support requests, interviewing, presenting, etc. But just after four months, now that I think about my time at Cisco, none of the actual work takes the centre stage in my memory. Instead, the memory is filled with incredible life stories I heard during the short walks I took at the park for one:one meetings, or relaxed and often-long Friday lunches, or giving someone a safe space when they felt vulnerable. It's a reminder that when it's all done and dusted - what remains is the people and relationships we build with them. I'm so glad to get this card in the mail after I left and I'll forever remember this kind gesture.</p>

<p>What better can a man wish for than being "unfrogettable"?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Where to Learn: 10 Ways I Do]]></title>
    <link href="http://smsohan.com/blog/2020/11/18/where-to-learn/"/>
    <updated>2020-11-18T10:51:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://smsohan.com/blog/2020/11/18/where-to-learn</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/learning.png" alt="learning" /></p>

<p>When talking to people, I'm always interested to know how they learn. This image above shows a view of how I personally learn. Here's some context about the items on the diagram:</p>

<ol>
<li>Online-courses: I love O'Reilly learning. Their video courses are split into 5 minute lectures. For example, I took their Kotlin course to learn the language.</li>
<li>Books: Books are great for curated content, but it takes dedicated time. Most of the time, I have one book that I read. Current interest is on leadership and business.</li>
<li>Hands-on: A lot of people learn by doing. I do the same, but mostly at a hello world level instead of going too deep into new things.</li>
<li>Podcasts: This is my most passive form of learning, mostly when I'm walking or driving.</li>
<li>People: I keep in touch with people and ask them about what they are learning.</li>
<li>Twitter: I admit, I spend too much time on Twitter. But occasionally, people share interesting things.</li>
<li>YouTube videos: I watch conference talks such as InfoQ, DotNet, Rails, Ruby, Goto, and AWS.</li>
<li>News: I follow Hacker News mostly for tech and business news. And then there's following stock market news about new business innovations.</li>
<li>Interviews: I watch inteview shows on YouTube as I'm a big fan of biographical content.</li>
<li>Open-source: I follow a bunch of open-source projects or just read code from time to time to learn about how the passionate and expert developers craft code.</li>
</ol>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Learn to Get and Give Feedback]]></title>
    <link href="http://smsohan.com/blog/2020/11/12/learn-to-get-and-give-feedback/"/>
    <updated>2020-11-12T11:45:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://smsohan.com/blog/2020/11/12/learn-to-get-and-give-feedback</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/feedback.jpg" alt="Feedback" /></p>

<p><small>Photo credits to <a href="https://flic.kr/p/2edx7Za">GotCredit</a></small></p>

<p>Here’s a personal story about getting a feedback. For context, English is my second language. I grew up speaking Bangla as my primary language. I learned reading and writing English in school - grammar first. I had only started speaking English much later in my life, in my mid-twenties. So, I often struggle with the informal form of the language. With this context, here’s an excerpt of a one:one chat conversation at work (from memory):</p>

<p><strong>Catherine</strong>: Sohan, I have a question when you have time.<br/>
<strong>Me</strong>: Shoot me.<br/>
<strong>Catherine</strong>: Haha. It’s not “shoot me”. I think you mean just “shoot”. When you say “shoot me” it means…</p>

<p>In this case, Catherine genuinely cared and had the courage to share this feedback about my improper use of English. I love getting such direct and timely feedback.</p>

<p>Here, I’m sharing links to some content that I found to be high quality resources to learn about  feedback. Hope you’ll enjoy.</p>

<ol>
<li>Radical Candor Talk - <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=4yODalLQ2lM">The Surprising Secret to Being a Good Boss</a></li>
<li>Podcast: <a href="https://podcasts.apple.com/ca/podcast/ep-7-how-to-get-feedback-from-your-boss/id1188489488?i=1000381196889">How to Get Feedback From Your Boss</a></li>
<li>Podcast: <a href="https://podcasts.apple.com/ca/podcast/ep-16-take-feedback-like-a-boss/id1188489488?i=1000384606048">Take Feedback Like A Boss</a></li>
<li>Podcast: <a href="https://podcasts.apple.com/ca/podcast/ep-8-how-to-give-feedback-to-your-boss/id1188489488?i=1000381487680">How to Give Feedback To Your Boss</a></li>
<li>Book chapter: <a href="https://www.norulesrules.com">Max up Candor: A Circle of Feedback</a></li>
</ol>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
